Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.) PE.039
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.)
1967-2001
1967-1971
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.039
2 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.) (1967-2001, bulk 1967-1971) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The Peace and Freedom Party (PFP) was established nationally in 1967 as an organization opposition to the Democratic Party and their support for the Vietnam War. The collection consists of printed matter put out by the PFP, generally at the state and city level, with the majority of the collection coming from New York and California. There are fliers, circular letters, brochures, and other printed matter, highlighting the PFP's involvement in national and state elections as they tried to build a viable third party alternative in the United States.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
The Peace and Freedom Party (PFP) is a minor left-leaning political party. The PFP was founded in June of 1967, though the first national convention was convened in the summer of 1968. It was there in Ann Arbor, Michigan that the group nominated Black Power leader Eldridge Cleaver as their candidate for U.S. President. The PFP arose in opposition to the Vietnam War and in support of civil rights, women's equality and rights for workers. The PFP is still active today, primarily in California, nominating Ralph Nader for president in 2008.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.) (1967-2001, bulk 1967-1971) provides a selection of printed material produced by the Peace and Freedom Party (PFP) at the city, state and national level. The bulk of the material in the collection comes from California and New York, consisting of position papers, fliers and outreach mailings for the 1967 registration drive for voters in California. There is also printed matter from the 1968 New York and California state conventions as well. There are notable fliers and other printed material documenting the Party's presidential campaigns for Eldridge Cleaver and Dick Gregory, as well as the congressional campaign for David McReynolds. Also included are party platforms and principles from the first national convention held in Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1968. There are numerous meeting and event fliers from New York City colleges and universities documenting the organization's role in progressive politics, including the student protests at Columbia, and the New York University Chapter's stance on Black Power, the Vietnam War and the democratic university.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library.
The accession number NPA.2005.028 is associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Third parties (United States politics); Brochures.; Fliers (printed matter); McReynolds, David; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998; Gregory, Dick; Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.)
- Albany and Troy Peace and Freedom Party (NY), 1969- (Box 1)
- Alameda County Peace and Freedom Movement (CA), 1968 (Box 1)
- Berkeley Peace and Freedom Movement (CA), undated (Box 1)
- Black and Brown Caucus, 1968- (Box 1)
- Brooklyn (NY), 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Buffalo (NY), 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- California State, 1968-2001 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 17)
- California State: Convention (Richmond, CA), Mar 1968 (Box 1)
- California State: Registration Drive (Berkeley), 1967 (Box 1)
- California State: Steering Committee I, 1968 (Box 1)
- California State: Steering Committee II, 1968 (Box 1)
- Cambridge Peace and Freedom Campaign (MA), circa 1968 (Box 1)
- Cleaver, Eldridge (presidential candidacy), 1968 (Box 1)
- Convention (Ann Arbor, MI) (first national), 1968 (Box 1)
- Dick Gregory for President Committee (CA), 1968 (Box 1)
- History and Publications on, 1968, undated (Box 1)
- Iowa, circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Illinois, 1968, undated (Box 1)
- Ithaca (NY), undated (Box 1)
- Labor Party Caucus, 1968 (Box 1)
- Manhattan (South, East, West, Lower) (New York, NY), 1968 (Box 1)
- McReynolds, David (New York, NY) (campaign), 1968 (Box 1)
- National Organizing Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
- National Peace and Freedom Party (news bulletin), undated (Box 1)
- New Mexico Peace and Freedom Movement, 1968 (Box 1)
- New York (NY) (city and state office), 1968 (Box 1)
- New York (NY) (city and state office), 1969, undated (Box 1)
- New York (NY): Meeting and Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- New York Organizing Committee, 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 18)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Convention, May 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Convention, Jul 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Convention I, Nov 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Convention II, Nov 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Delegates Assembly, 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Interim Administrative Committee, 1968 (Box 1)
- New York State Peace and Freedom Party: Steering Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- NYU Peace and Freedom Party, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Oneonta Peace and Freedom (NY), 1968 (Box 1)
- Peace and Freedom Summer Project, undated (Box 1)
- Principles (adopted at national convention), 1968 (Box 2)
- Queens Peace and Freedom Party Club, 1968, undated (Box 2, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 19)
- Rochester Peace and Freedom (NY), undated (Box 2)
- San Francisco Peace and Freedom (CA), 1968-1969, undated (Box 2)
- Student Committee (various New York City colleges), 1968-1969 (Box 2)
- Syracuse Peace and Freedom Party (NY), 1969 (Box 2)
- Venice Organizing Project (CA), 1968-1969 (Box 2)
- Village-Chelsea Peace and Freedom Party (New York, NY), 1968, undated (Box 2, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 20)
- Washington State Peace and Freedom Party, undated (Box 2)